<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The rarities of Russia with the interest of England in point of trade with that country which occasioned the magnificent entertainments of the Russian ambassadours, 1. by Queen Elizabeth, anno 1589, 2. by King James, November 5, 1617, 3. by King Charles the Second, 1662, which are here described / by Will. White merchant.</title>
            <author>White, Will. (William), merchant.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65810</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1857</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38600</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17805240</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17805240</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106636</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65810)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106636)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1109:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The rarities of Russia with the interest of England in point of trade with that country which occasioned the magnificent entertainments of the Russian ambassadours, 1. by Queen Elizabeth, anno 1589, 2. by King James, November 5, 1617, 3. by King Charles the Second, 1662, which are here described / by Will. White merchant.</title>
                  <author>White, Will. (William), merchant.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 32 [i.e. 26] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errors in paging: p. 7-8, 21-24 ommited in numbering only.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Russia --  Economic conditions --  To 1861.</term>
               <term>Soviet Union --  Description and travel.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106636:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE RARITIES OF RUSSIA WITH THE Intereſt of England In point of Trade with that Country: Which occaſioned the magnificent Entertainments of the <hi>R<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SSIAN</hi> AMBASSADOURS;</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. By Queen <hi>Elizabeth, Anno</hi> 1589.</item>
               <item>2. By King <hi>James, November</hi> 5. 1617.</item>
               <item>3. By King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, 1662.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Which are here deſcribed:</p>
            <p>By <hi>WILL. WHITE</hi> Merchant.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Author. 1662.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:106636:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:106636:2"/>
            <head>THE PARITIES OF <hi>R<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SSIA</hi> and <hi>M<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SGOVIA.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Commerce and correſpondencie of humane nature <hi>ſubſiſts</hi> by this: <hi>Viz.</hi> that each proper Countrey hath a want which another Countreys Commodity may ſupply; and a ſupply which another Countrey may want: ſo that one part may not ſay to the other, <hi>I have no need of thee:</hi> Fruitful <hi>Europe</hi> may not ſay to barren <hi>America, I have no need of thee;</hi> nor rich <hi>America</hi> to poorer <hi>Aſia, I have no need of thee:</hi> the fertile South cannot ſay to the North, <hi>I have no need of thee;</hi> nor the North to the South, <hi>I have no need of thee:</hi> that there ſhould be no Schiſme in the great body of the world, but that the ſeveral Parts of it ſhould have the ſame care one for another: And ſeeing mankind is but one fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, (for God hath made of one blood all Nations of the earth, for to dwell upon the face of the earth, and hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined the times before appointed, and the place of their <hi>habitation</hi>) the World a great houſe, ſundry Countreys ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral rooms, it is fit that we who are in the Parlour ſhould
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:106636:3"/>know the out-lodgings of this great houſe; and the world be acquainted with it ſelf, before it be diſſolved from it ſelf at the day of judgment. That part of the world called <hi>Ruſſia</hi> or <hi>Muſcovia</hi> (which hath thought it its <hi>Intereſt</hi> to <hi>court</hi> us with an <hi>Ambaſſadour civilly,</hi> whom we have thought our <hi>intereſt</hi> to entertain <hi>honourably</hi>) hath theſe peculiar Rarities and Commodities.</p>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>Of the Soyle and Climate.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>R<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſſia</hi> or <hi>Muſcovia,</hi> formerly called <hi>Sarmatia,</hi> called ſo from <hi>Buſſe,</hi> in that Language to divide, becauſe it was divided among eight Brethren and Siſters, lyeth Northward to <hi>Lapland</hi> and the North Ocean, Eaſtward and Southward towards <hi>Tartaria,</hi> Weſtward and South-Weſtward towards <hi>Lithuania, Livonia,</hi> and <hi>Poland,</hi> having thirty Shires far more large, though thinner inhabited then <hi>England,</hi> which are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided into four Juriſdictions, called Chelfirds, or four Ports: This Countrey is in length four thouſand five hundred ſixty five miles, and in breadth three thouſand nine hundred and thirteen; a vaſt compaſſe if it were well peopled, that would hardly be well governed by him, or well indured by his Neighbours: Indeed the ſoyl being ſlight and ſandy all over, and Northward very barren, is much of it a Deſart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood for wild Beaſts, rather then an habitation for Men; only the Emperour garriſons the borders, leaſt an Enemy preſuming upon the ſolitude, might think to have a fair and clear footing for forreign Enemies to faſten on this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and from thence eaſily to invade the neighbouring Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:106636:3"/>
                  <hi>(a thin Meadow being quickly mowed:)</hi> And more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over the <hi>Cham Tartar</hi> will neither himſelf plant Townes to dwell there, living a wild and vagrant life, nor ſuffer the <hi>Ruffe,</hi> who is far off, to people thoſe Ports; though no doubt ſo vaſt a Countrey would maintain its people, if the wildneſs thereof were tamed with husbandry: but theſe people ſcorning that their ground ſhould be better civilized then themſelves, never ſuffer it to be manured, being more willing to provide their bread with the Sword then with the Plough: but for ſeventeen hundred mile Northward, Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and Southward of <hi>Moſcho,</hi> it is fruitful and pleaſant for Paſture, Corn, Wood, Water, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in great plenty: this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey is like a piece of Cloth fine in the woof, and coarſe in the liſts; fruitful in the body of it, and barren in the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. For five moneths together, <hi>viz.</hi> from <hi>November</hi> to <hi>April,</hi> the whole Countrey is covered with Snow a yard or two deep; and with Froſt a yard thick, ſo cold, that if you hold a Pewter-diſh in your hand, your fingers will freeze to it, and you muſt leave your skin behind you at parting: If you throw water up into the air, it comes down ice: if you breath, it will be ſo thick that it is ready to ſtifle you with the cold: ſo that it is uſual for poor men to fall down in the ſtreets and marſhes; and the Beaſts not enduring the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Deſarts, come in troops upon the Cities, and make them Deſarts too: Yet towards Summer the Countrey is ſo freſh and flouriſhing, the Trees (which are for the moſt part Fern and Bent) ſo ſweet and beautiful; the Flowers ſo va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious; the Meadows ſo green; the Birds (eſpecially the Nightingale, which ſings more lowd and artificially there then in other Countreys) ſo merry, that you would think Paradiſe were ſtarted up there on a ſudden: The reaſon of which ſudden Verdure is this, that the Snow (which keeps it warm in the Winter, cloathing it againſt the Froſt) melt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Spring, doth drench and ſoak the ground, that it
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:106636:4"/>is, as I told, of a ſleight and ſandy mould; and then the Sun ſhineth ſo hotly upon that, that it draweth out the Hearbs &amp; Plants in that great plenty and variety as is at once our <hi>won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> and our <hi>pleaſure;</hi> the Countrey beſides having the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of Springs, Rivers, and Lakes, which are ſome ſixty, ſome eighty, ſome an hundred miles in length; and the Summer there is as much over-hot as the Winter is over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cold. Their Rivers are 1. <hi>Volghu,</hi> ariſing out of the root of an Alder-tree, and in two hundred miles improving an Engliſh mile in breadth. 2. <hi>Neper,</hi> called formerly <hi>Boriſther,</hi> is that which divideth the Countrey from <hi>Lithuania,</hi> and falleth into the <hi>Euxine</hi> Sea. The third is <hi>Don a Taxais</hi> (the ancient bounder of <hi>Europe</hi> and <hi>Aſia</hi>) which runneth through the <hi>Cham Tartars</hi> Countrey into the great Sea, the Lake cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Maeotis,</hi> by which a man may go from <hi>Moske</hi> to <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople.</hi> The fourth is <hi>Duina,</hi> ſome hundred miles long, which falls Northward into the Bay of St. <hi>Nicholas,</hi> and hath great Alabaſter Rocks on the banks towards the Sea-ſide; and other Rivers, the leaſt as big as the <hi>Thames</hi> in bigneſs, and in length far bigger: The Pole at <hi>Moſcho</hi> is 55. degrees, 10. minutes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Of the Native Commodities.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. THeir Fruits are Apples, Pears, Plums, Cherries, and Cidern like a Muskmelon, but more ſweet and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, Cucumbers, Goords, Raſps, Strawberries, and Hurtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berries, and many other Berries in Woods and Hedges.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:106636:4"/>
               <p n="2">2. Their Grain is Wheat, Rye, Barly, Oats, Peaſe, Buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, Iſnythu, a grain like Rice, which they ſell at three pence a buſhelmoſt commonly, unleſs rather by reaſon of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities monopoly then the Earths barrenneſs, there happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a dearth, and then their Corn is twenty pence a buſhel.</p>
               <p n="1">1. But the Commodities wherewith they enrich them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and pleaſure other Countries, is, firſt Furrs of all ſorts, as Buck, Fox, Sables, Dun Fur, Mortrones, Ermines, Miniver, Bever, Wulverin, Squirrel, whereof there is tranſported out of the Countrey by the Merchants of <hi>Turky</hi> and Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to the value of ſeven hundred thouſand Rubbels.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſecond Commodity is Honey, whereof beſides an exceeding great quantity ſpent in their ordinary drinks, which is <hi>Mead</hi> of all ſorts, and other uſes, a good quantity is carried out of the Countrey to the neighbouring parts which have need of it: God hath not given <hi>all Commodities</hi> to one, to elate it with pride, and none to other Countries, to deject them with penſiveneſs, but there is ſome kind of equallity between the profits of Countries, to continue Commerce and ballance Trade in ſome proportion.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The third Commodity is Wax, whereof there hath been tranſported a millions worth abroad: this Wax is the cask, where Honey is the liquour, and being yellow by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, is by Art made white and green; for ſight the cleareſt, for ſmell the ſweeteſt, for touch the cleanlieſt; uſeful in Law to ſeal Inſtruments; in Phyſick to mollifie Sinews, ripen and diſſolue Ulcers; the ground of all Searcloaths, called ſo from <hi>Cera</hi> Wax: Here are Lakes of Honey found in hollow trees; and Combes eight foot long: the Heaths have the worſt Honey, and the Champion the beſt: the finer the Wheat and the Wool, the poorer the Honey: the beſt Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney is loweſt in the veſſel: <hi>The beſt Oyl is at top, the beſt Wine in the middle, and the beſt Honey is in the bottome:</hi> It
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:106636:5"/>opneeth Obſtructions, cleareth the Breaſts of thoſe humours that fall down from the Head, looſeneth the Belly, and hath other good qualities not to be reckoned in a Winters day.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The fourth Commodity is Cow-hides; <hi>Adam</hi>'s firſt ſhute was of leaves, his ſecond of leather. It is a common ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, that when Wheat is dear Leather is cheap; and when Leather is dear, Wheat is cheap: their Loſh or Buffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hide is large and fair; their Bull or Cow-hide (for they have no Oxen nor Weathers) is ſmall; there hath been tranſported by Merchants an hundred thouſand Hides.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The fifth is their Meath, a drink made of Water, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and other Ingredients moſt wholſome for Mans body: <hi>Pollio</hi> being an hundred yeares old, and asked by <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> by what meanes eſpecially he had ſo long preſerved his vigour both of mind and body, anſwered, <hi>Intus mulſo, foris Oleo, By taking Metheglin inward, and Oyl outward.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. The ſixt Commodity is Tallow, whereof they tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſport a great weight; their paſturage being ſo good, their faſts ſo many, and their uſe of Tallow ſo little; there hath been ſhipped of this commodity two millions worth to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign parts.</p>
               <p n="7">7. As their Beaſts fat yeilds them the ſixt, ſo their Fiſh the ſeventh Commodity; <hi>viz.</hi> Train-oyl, which they draw out of the Seale-fiſh, the Sturgeon, the Sterledey, the Sevengu, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which they take thus; before Winter they leave their Boats near the Bay of St. <hi>Nicholas,</hi> and at Spring they come and find the fiſh haunt and ſholes, and ſo environ them and kill them by force, giving warning to all the Companies by firing a Beacon when they have diſcovered a haunt.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Their eighth Commodity is Sturgeon and other Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſh, caught in thoſe Northern Seas in abundance: the little head and Swines back is the ſign that theſe fiſh are in ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:106636:5"/>
               <p n="9">9 The ninth Commodity is Flaxe and Hempe, which hath amounted to 800000. yearly, this is ſold for cordage, ſo neceſſary for us, that it is a common Proverbe when Hempe is ſpun, then <hi>England</hi> is done; when all that neceſſary Commodity is employed ſo that there is no more left for Sailes and Cordages, <hi>England</hi> (whoſe ſtrength conſiſts in Shipping) would be reduced to a wofull <hi>condition;</hi> and I wonder there is not more Hempe ſowed among us ſince our Land affords ſo much ſtrong and deep ground proper for the ſame; here is excellent Flaxe which well husbanded would find Linnen for the Rich, and living for the Poor.</p>
               <p n="10">10 Their tenth Commodity is Salt, their beſt Salt is a <hi>Stararouſe</hi> in very great quantity, where they have great ſtore of Salt-wells about 200 miles from the Sea; at <hi>Aſtracan</hi> Salt is made naturally by the Sea water caſting it up in heapes, and ſo it is digged down, and carried away by the Merchants; this is moſt eſſential to mans livelyhood, without which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sacrifice was <hi>pleaſing</hi> to God, nor meate ſavory <hi>to man,</hi> it is placed on the Board with bread, to ſhew that they are equally neceſſary to mans ſuſtinance; and it is obſerved that,</p>
               <p n="1">1 Some Countryes have Salt without fleſh within many miles, as in the South part of <hi>Africa;</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 Some have plenty of Fleſh but no Salt to make uſe thereof, as in many parts of <hi>Tartary;</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 Some have Fleſh and Salt, but the Fleſh utterly uncapable of ſeaſoning as at <hi>Nombre de Dios;</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4 Some have Fleſh and Salt but the Salt ſo dear
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:106636:6"/>that common people cannot compaſſe it as in <hi>France;</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5 Some have Fleſh, caple of Salt, and Salt at an eaſy rate as they in <hi>Muſcovy</hi> and we in <hi>England, Foelices bona ſi ſua norint.</hi>—</p>
               <p n="10">10. The tenth Commodity is Tarre which they make out of their Firre Trees, in the Country of <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yna</hi> and <hi>Smolexſho,</hi> whereof much is ſent abroad.</p>
               <p n="11">11. The leventh Commodity is Oake, when the Spies were ſent into the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> among other inſtructions given them, they had order to make enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry whether there was Wood therein or not, this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try affordeth abundance of Wood, excellent for Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and other uſes.</p>
               <p n="12">12 The twelfth Commodity is <hi>Barley</hi> white large plumpe and full of Flower, it is (though not ſo tooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome) yet as wholeſome as Wheat it ſelfe, and was all the ſtaffe of Bread which <hi>Chriſts</hi> Body leaned upon all his life, eating to atteſt his Humanity, <hi>Barley loaves</hi> to evince his humility.</p>
               <p n="13">13 The next Commodity is Diamonds in black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and hardneſſe for ſhort of the <hi>Indian,</hi> yet ſet with a good foile (advantaged hypocriſie paſſeth often for ſincerity) may at the firſt ſight deceive no unskilfull lapidary, as their luſtre is leſſe then Orient Diamonds, ſo herein they exceed them that nature hath made both their face and their dreſſe by whom they are pointed and poliſhed.</p>
               <p n="14">14 Amber-greeſe ſo precious a Commodity as is fixed to no place in the World, as too great a treaſure for any one Country to engroſſe, and therefore it is only fluctuating and caſually found by ſmall parcells,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:106636:6"/>ſometimes in one place, ſometimes in another, yet much of it is found upon the Coaſts of <hi>Muſcovy;</hi> it's by ſome thought to be the ſperme of a Fiſh; by others the royling of ſea water; by others a gumme growing on the ſea ſhore, however it is very refreſhing for the ſpirits, and Soveraign for the ſtrengthning of the Head, beſides the moſt fragrant ſcent, for ſtronger in conſort, when compounded with other things, then when ſingly it ſelfe.</p>
               <p n="15">15 The fifteenth Commodity is Metall which of all ſorts is found with much ado in theſe parts eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally Iron and it's elder brother ſteel extracted from the ſame Oare, differing from it not in kind but in degree of purity as being the firſt running thereof, it's more hard and brittle then the Metalls of other Countryes.</p>
               <p n="16">16 Fiſh tooth called <hi>Ribazuba,</hi> the powder where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is good againſt poyſon, which makes Beades Knives, and ſwords, Hafts for noble Men and Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, two foot in length, and weigh eleven or twelve pound a peice.</p>
               <p n="17">17 Neer <hi>Dudia</hi> is a ſoft Rock called <hi>Slude</hi> which cut to thin peices ſerveth inſtead of Glaſſe and Horne and gives a clearer light,</p>
               <p n="18">18 They have Fallow Deer, Roe Bucks great ſtore their Staggs are ſtately Creatures, jealous and revenge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, inſomuch that a Stagge unable for the preſent to maſter another, who had taken his Hind from him, waited his opportunity, till his enemy had weakened himſelfe with his wantonneſſe and then killed him; their Fleſh muſt needs be good whoſe very Hornes are accounted Cordiall, beſides there is a concave in the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:106636:7"/>neck of a green headed ſlagge, when above his <hi>firſt croſting</hi> wherein are many wormes ſome two inches in length, very uſefull in Phyſick and therefore lay'd up by many diſcreet perſons.</p>
               <p n="19">19. There Beaſts of ſtrange kind are the Laſh, the Ollen, the wild Horſe, the Bear, the Wolvering or Wood Dog, the Lyſerne, the Beaver, the Siabt, the Martron, the blacke and dun Fox, the white Bear to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the ſea-coaſt of <hi>Pechora,</hi> the Gurn-ſtate, the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niver, their Hores and Squirells which are of the uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all colour in ſummer, but the one turnes white, and the other Gray in Winter, ſome Heathen have cauſleſly complained of nature as a ſtep mother to Mankind, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe other creatures come into the World cloathed with Furres and Feathers whileſt man is expoſed naked to the world, I ſay a cauſeleſſe charge becauſe what the Beaſts have by nature we wear by art, the Furre they wore when alive, we wear when they are dead.</p>
               <p n="20">20 For Birds they have diverſe of the principall kind, as Hawkes, Eagles, the Ger-faulcon the ſlight Faulcon, the Goſhawke, the Taſſet, the ſpar-Hawke the ſtorke, the Crane, the Teddor, the Pheaſant and Patridge, and the great Owle; <hi>Muſcovy</hi> may be called the Aviary of the World, where the wild Fowle are remarkeable for, 1 Plenty, ſo that ſome ten thouſand ſmall Birds have been caught at a draught; 2 Variety no man being able to give them their proper names, except one ſhould get <hi>Adames</hi> Nomenclator of Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; 3 Delſciouſneſſe, wild Fowle being more dainty and digeſtable then tame of the ſame kind as ſpending their groſſy humors, with their activity and conſtant motion in flying,</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:106636:7"/>
               <p n="21">21 They have all freſh water Fiſh, as Pikes, the freſh water Wolves, and therefore an old pond-Pike is a diſh of more ſtate then profit to the Owners; ſeeing a Pikes belly is a little Fiſh-pond, where leſſer of all ſorts have been contained, although tyrants are ſhort liv'd, yet Pikes live ſix ſcore yeares, this Fiſh they ſay cheweth the Cud, is fine and wholeſome, and the leſs the ſweet carps which were brought thence to <hi>England</hi> in King <hi>Hen.</hi> the 8th. time; Trouts, pleaſant and wholeſome Fiſh as whoſe feeding is pure and cleanly in the ſwifteſt ſtreames and on the hardeſt gravell, they are in their Perfection in <hi>May,</hi> and yearly decline with the Buck, Eeles which loves not the Ruſſe as well he loves them, ſo true is the <hi>Italian</hi> Proverbe <hi>give Eeles without Wine to your exemies Pilchards,</hi> plenty whereof are taken in theſe parts, perſecuted to the ſhore by their enemies the ſunny and <hi>Hawke,</hi> till in purſuance of their revenge they all become a prey to the Fiſher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, their numbers are incredible, employing a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of poor people, in pulling, gutting, ſplitting powdering and drying them, and then with Oyle and a Lemon, they are meate for greateſt Noble man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, <hi>Tenches</hi> Fiſh that love ponds better then Rivers, and Pits better then either; it's pleaſant in <hi>Taſh</hi> and is called by ſome the Phyſician or ſurgeon of Fiſh, it cures the Pike, and therefore the Pike they ſay ſpares it; and other Fiſh, as the Bellonga, the ſturge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the ſeverign, and ſterledy out of the rowes of which four Fiſh they make great ſtore of caveare, they have White and Red ſammon, a dainty and wholeſome Fiſh, and a double riddle in nature.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:106636:8"/>
               <p>Firſt for its inviſible feeding, no man alive having found any meaſure in the maw thereof: ſecondly for its ſtrang leaping and ſhooring it ſelf out of the water an Incredible heigth and Length: and they ſay it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth from a ſpawn to a full grown fiſh, within the compaſſe of a year: plenty of theſe in their ports though not in ſuch abundance as in <hi>Scotland,</hi> where ſervants they ſay Indent with their maſters, not to be fed therewith above thrice a week—The <hi>Herring,</hi> a fiſh though Contemptible in its ſelf, Conſiderable in its company, ſwiming in ſuch ſholes that what the <hi>Whale</hi> hath in bigneſſe the <hi>Herring</hi> hath in Number: yea red Herrings which in <hi>England</hi> are eated for ſauce, to quicken the appetite, ſerve in theſe ports for food to ſatisfy hunger.</p>
               <p>The laſt Commodity is Fuſtian Kerſy and other kind of Stuffes made cheifly in thoſe Ports and thence brought hither.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>There Religion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AS for their religion for which we ought to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine them: Its not depraved by ſuperſtition, Idolatry, and uſurpation of the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> but according the poorer way of the Greek Church, they own the ſcriptures and the 4 firſt councells toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with to the purer wayes of the primitive times: they are governed by one Patrion of <hi>Chio,</hi> and works, by 4 Arch Biſhops, by threeſcore Biſhops with there aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtants, there Clergy are very ignorant and unwill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to take any paines to teach the people, but they read a Lyturgy, and adminiſter the ſacraments: there
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:106636:8"/>Lyturgy begins with theſe words, <hi>Bleſſe O heavenly Paſtour,</hi> meaning Chriſt, <hi>In the name of the Father,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Lord have mercy upon us,</hi> &amp;c, then in Chancel, ſaith the Lords Prayer, and a donology to the trinity: then the Pſalms for the day, then they read Chapters: the Commandments, and <hi>Athanaſies</hi> his Creed; and then they pray: there children are Baptized within 8 days after they are born: the Sacrament of the Lords<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſupper is adminiſtred but once a year a little before Eaſter, very ſolemnly all going to it with confeſſion of ſins: the bread is put in the wine and ſo adminiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: there was one endeavour to unite them to the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in the year 1588. but it failed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the many Corruptions in doctrine and diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline which they found in that Church. And at the ſame time, and ever ſince they have endeavoured to make leagues offenſive and defenſive. With all Chriſtian Princes that they might be able to grapple with the great enemy of the faith, the <hi>Turke,</hi> to the advancement of Religion, the propagation of the Goſpel, and the converſion of the world: if any object that Religion is not to be beaten into turn with the Dint of ſword, yet it may be Lawfull to open the the way force, for inſtruction, catechiſing, &amp; ſuch other gentle by means to follow after: however if we do not offend the Infidel, we may defend our ſelves and a preventive war, grounded upon a juſt fear of Invaſion is Lawful. Its beſt being before hand with an enemy, Leaſt the medicine come too Late for the malady: In ſuch dangers to play an aftergame is rather a ſhift then a policy, eſpecially ſeeing war is a tragedy, that allwayes deſtroyeth the Stage whereon it is acted: It
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:106636:9"/>is the moſt adviſed way, not to waite for the enemy, but to ſeek him out in his own Country.</p>
               <p>They own the Scriptures in their own Language, they leand too much on the authority of the Church: they hold a juſtification by faith, working by love: they think a man cannot be aſſured of his ſalvation un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ill he dye, they make ſome difference of meats and drinkes: they hold a neceſſity of Baptizme as without which no ſalvation: the allow prieſts marriages: they own 3 Sacraments, the one of Baptizme, the other of the Lords Supper, the third of extream unction: they honour the <hi>Engliſh</hi> way of profeſſion: in ſo much as one of them ſaid to a ſervant of Mr. <hi>Fletchers,</hi> who writ the hiſtory of <hi>Ruſſia: that God had given to Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land light to day,</hi> and <hi>might give it to morrow if he pleaſe to them:</hi> for <hi>Marriage:</hi> The perſons to <hi>be</hi> mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried are not to ſee one another untill they <hi>are</hi> married: There friends muſt woe for them: and when they have agreed of a dowry, they are married in the Church after the manner of other Churches: but the bride and the bridegroom are to be very modeſt, a great while after the marriage: and the woman is to have ſo much dowry as ſhe hath children: In a word they agree with us in the moſt weighty points of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: whereupon the Papiſt condemne them for Haereticks and Caſtawayes, and killing more then a third of all Chriſtians, (as <hi>Cain</hi> did a quarter of mankind with a blow) with this their uncharitable Cenſure: but we muſt not with Raſh judging throw all into the pit of hell, whom we ſee walking near the brink thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:106636:9"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>The Borderers of</hi> Ruſſia, <hi>with whom they have moſt to doe in War and Peace.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THat we may know our Intereſt in a good Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence with <hi>Ruſſia;</hi> we are to underſtand who are the People that the <hi>Ruſſia</hi> hath moſt to doe with in Warre and Peace; and ſo we may know what uſe we may make of them in our Dealing with Foreign Nations; In <hi>Aſia</hi> they have to doe with the <hi>Tartar,</hi> In <hi>Europe</hi> with the <hi>Polonian, Swede, Hungarian,</hi> and <hi>Dane,</hi> where theſe <hi>Ruſſia</hi> may do us many conſiderable ſervices; being ready (as occaſion ſerves) to uſe their Intereſt of Power <hi>over,</hi> or friendſhip <hi>with</hi> theſe Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to our advantage: Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> made uſe of the <hi>Muſcovite</hi> to divirt the Emperor from aſſiſting the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> in the Year, 1588.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Their warlike Furniture.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FOr the Incouragement of the ſouldiery, every Souldier in Ruſſia is a Gentleman, and none gentlemen but the ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers: and when any is of years he preſents himſelf to the great conſtable who admits him to the ſervice, and alloweth as much Land as his father had: for there is Land to maintaine the Army, &amp; all that are not of the Army muſt uſe ſome vulger
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:106636:10"/>wayes to live for they are allowed no Land: the Emperour hath 15000. Horſemen for ſtanding penſioners: and he hath 110. Noblemen who are to find amongſt them 65000. horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men with all neceſſaries meet for the war after the Ruſſia man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: and theſe 65000 Horſemen are to march to the borders of the Chrim Tarter: whether there be warrs with the Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars or no, and whereas it might be thought dangerous for the Noblemen to have ſo good forces under there Commands the <hi>Emperor</hi> prevents all Inconveniences, 1. By changing their noble-men as he thinks good. 2. By making them live and depend upon him, they being ſuch as have but a ſmall Eſtate of their own. 3. And they are ſeldome ſouldiers themſelves, there charge being only to ſee the Army Paid. If there be need of any greater number, he entertaines thoſe men that are out of pay, and given charge to his Noble-men, that hold Lands of him to bring into the field every man a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poportionable of his ſervants and ſuch as till his hand. with their furniture according to the juſt number he intends to make, when the ſervice being done preſently Lay in their weapons, and return to there ſervile occupations againe, of footmen he hath 12000. whereof 5000 guard <hi>Moſco:</hi> and two thouſand attend at Court: the reſt he diſpoſeth of in his Gariſons, untill he hath occaſion for them in the field: And receive for Sallery 6. pound a year apeice, beſides twelve meaſures of <hi>Rie,</hi> and Oales; They employ ſome 12000. ſtrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, <hi>Poland, Dutch, Scotch,</hi> &amp;c. upon the borders of <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary,</hi> and ſome <hi>Mercenary Tartars</hi> upon the borders of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Sweden,</hi> thinks it pollicy ſo to uſe their ſervice upon Contrary borders; the Generall is uſually a noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of great extraction, but of mean parts: For in this point, they are very wary that nobility and power <hi>meet not both in one,</hi> eſpecially if they ſee wiſedome withall or apt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for policy to make up the defect In the Generall, there is ſome other joyned with him as Leivtennant general of farre leſſe nobility, but of far more valour and experience then he in Marſhall affaires: who ordereth all things that the other
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:106636:10"/>Countenanceth. And he is asſiſted by 4 Marſhals of the field, and theſe fear have two under each of them, that twice a week at leaſt muſter and train their ſeverall wings or bands, and give juſtice for all faults &amp; diſorders Committed, in the Camp: They have a great Maſter of the Ordinance and a Scout-Maſter Generall who hath a 1000 men about him to ſpy abroad; all theſe Officers muſt attend the Generall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day, to put him in mind of thoſe things that may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern their offices.</p>
               <p>Upon any War the 4 Lords of the Chetsfinds ſends their ſummons to be Proclaimed in the cheif Towns of the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire</hi> to all Gentlemens Sons to meet at the boders at ſuch a place, and at ſuch a time to be there Inrolled by certain Officers appointed by the high Conſtable.</p>
               <p>If any man makes default, and faile at the day he is puniſhed very ſeverely; When the Soudiers are aſſembled they are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided into Bands and Companies, and thoſe Companies are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced into 4 legions under the four great Feild Marſhalls who are all under him, who hath a Commiſſion with inſtructions for the preſent ſervice, they are armed but ſlightly with Bow and Arrow and a ſword, and here and there one with a Coat of Male; the cheife Commanders go very richly with their Saddles of cloath of Gold, their Bridles fair boſſed and taſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeled with Gold and Silke Fringe, beſtuded with Pearle and precious ſtones themſelves in very fair Armour of ſhining ſteel yet covered commonly with cloath of gold, and edged round with Ermin Furre, with a ſteel Helmet upon their heads of great price, theſe ſwords, Bows, and arrowes by there ſides, their Speares in their hands, with other Helmets, and the Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Septer carried before them; the footman hath nothing but his peice in his hand, his ſtriking hatched at his back, and his Sword by his ſide; every man is to provide for himſelfe ſufficient for 4 moneths, and if need be to give order for more to be brought to him from his Tenant that tilleth his ground to the Campe, they are prepared to be Souldiers before hand their proviſion is dryed bread &amp; Bacon with other dryed fleſh or fiſh after the <hi>Duch</hi> faſhion: The <hi>Ruſſin</hi> is not ſo hard to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:106636:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>an enterprize as he is to endure hardſhip, courage in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution failes him partly becauſe of his ſervile condition which will not ſuffer any courage to grow in him, and partly for lack of due honour and regard, which he hath no great hope of what ſoever ſervice or execution he doeth; their marching or leading is without order, onely they keep in 4 legions, and ſo thruſt onward in a hurry, tuhrſting rather to their number then their order, when they give any charge they make a great hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low and noiſe with Drums and Trumpets, and Swords bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhed over their Heads, their Footmen (becauſe commonly they want order in leading) are uſually placed in ſome ambuſh or place of advantage, where they may moſt annoy the enemy with leaſt hurt to themſelves; they have Caſtles of boards of 3, 4, 5, 6, or. 7 mile length to defend them on both ſides from Arrowes, in which they ſtand and have roome enough to charge and diſcharge their peices and to uſe their other Weapons; it is cloſe at both ends, and made with Loop-holes on either ſide, to lay out the noſe of their peice or to puſh forth any other Weapon, it's taken in peices and laid on Carts, ſparred toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and drawn by Horſes that are not ſeen, be covered with theſe carriage as with a pant-houſe, when it is brought to the place where it is to be uſed which is choſen out by the walking generall, it is planted as much as the preſent uſe requireth, ſometimes two miles long ſometimes more, which is ſoon done without the help of any Carpenter, becauſe the Timber is ſo framed to claſpe together one peice within another, as is eaſily underſtood by thoſe that know the manner of the <hi>Ruſſia</hi> build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, becauſe of their diſorder, the <hi>Ruſſia</hi> are obſerved better at defending a Town or caſtle, then at an open War in an open Field; it's thought there is no Prince in <hi>Chriſtendome</hi> hath bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter proviſion there the <hi>Ruſſia</hi> Emper our; as may partly appear by the Artillery at <hi>Moſco,</hi> where are of all ſorts of great Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, all Braſſe peices very fair, to an exceeding great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; a peice of gold ſtamped with St. <hi>George</hi> hanging on the Sleeves is the reward of the greateſt ſervice; Colonies are filled with garriſons, the Inhabitants being permitted upon their good behaviour to till the Land for the uſe of his garriſons which are maintained at the charge of thoſe Inhabitants.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:106636:11"/>
               <p>The Emperor of <hi>Ruſſia</hi> is of an <hi>Hungarian</hi> extracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon this token;
<note place="margin">The Ruſſe Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> That the Emperour once com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting ſome Bullion to an Engliſh Goldſmith, ſaid to him, look to thy weights, <hi>For my Ruſſes are all theeves;</hi> at which the Engliſhman ſmiling, the Emperor asked him what he ſmiled at, ſaith he, when you ſaid the <hi>Ruſſe</hi> were all theeves, you forgot that you were a <hi>Ruſſe;</hi> nay, ſaith he, you are deceaved, I am no <hi>Ruſſe</hi> but a <hi>German:</hi> He was Duke a great while, till about an hundred years ago he took upon him the Title of Emperor, about which time there was like to be great alteration in the <hi>Ruſſe</hi> Eſtate becauſe of a failure, in the time the Emperor being barren: And his brother like to be made away, his nurſe who taſted his meat being poyſoned,
<note place="margin">His Inau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guration.</note> this Emperor being inaugurated by the Patriarch and Clergy with the applauſe of the Nobility, Gentry and people, and prayed for him ſolemnly; thus, Preſerve, O Lord, under thy holy protection, keep him that he may do good and holy things; Let Juſtice ſhine forth in his dayes, that we may live quietly without ſtrife and malice, this in a ſoft voice to which he addeth a loud, <hi>Thou art the King of the whole world, and the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour of our ſouls,</hi> to thee the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt be all praiſe for ever and ever; then he puts on the Robe and the Cap in the <hi>Name of the Father, &amp;c.</hi> then the Deacon addes many years <hi>to the Noble Juan, Good, Honourable, beloved of God,</hi> Duke of &amp;c. whereto the other Prieſt anſwers, <hi>many years, many years to &amp;c.</hi> then they thundered out many <hi>years to the Noble Juan, Good, Honourable, beloved of God, &amp;c.</hi> He hath a very long Title at his Coronation of half a ſheet, which all Embaſſadors muſt repeat; on a good token that when Maſter <hi>Flecher</hi> in Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi> time had
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:106636:12"/>audience, he uſed but two or three Titles, whereupon the Chancellor never left chaſing till he gave his Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter order to repeat the reſt.</p>
               <p>All power is in the Emperor and his Counſel,
<note place="margin">Power.</note> and a few of the Biſhops to deceive the people who think all is well that goeth through the Biſhops hands, who preſcribe to the Parliament what they ſhall do; all places are beſtowed by the Emperor himſelf or his chief Favourite and relation during his pleaſure onely, he executes a man without judgment or trial: all par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons are from the Emperor, wherein the Empreſſe u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually appears very much.</p>
               <p>The Parliament confiſts of twenty Noble men,
<note place="margin">The Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> and as many Biſhops with the Emperor himſelf; no body repreſenting the people who are looked upon as ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants and ſlaves, the Clergy men being asked their opinion ſay; <hi>The Emperor and his Counſel are of great wiſdome, and they are not able to adviſe them: they can onely pray for them according to their duty and calling;</hi> then one of them asks the Emperors mind; the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary tells them, that the Emperor deſireth them to ſpeak their minds freely; then without any pauſe they conſent, and then the matter agreed on is drawn up by the Secreiaries to Proclamation to be publiſhed throughout the Empire.</p>
               <p>The Nobility hold all they have from the Emperor,
<note place="margin">Policy.</note> and they are kept under by emulation one of the other which the Emperor cunningly improveth to the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Nobles, who have liberty to deſtroy and undo one another upon private quarrels, that they may not be able to cope with the Emperor; the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror pretends to wafile ſome ſelect men in the book of his Favourites which he ſhews to others, that they
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:106636:12"/>may envy and undermine them; which begets a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal hatred betwixt them to pleaſure the Emperor: he moreover removes them from Country to Country, that they may never gain any love, authority, or po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pularitie, and their Eſtates are not above 2000 <abbr>l.</abbr> a year. There are four Provinces, and four Officers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to them, who attend the Emperor with all the buſineſs of thoſe Provinces, and communicate to the Provinces by their under Officers the Emperors plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure concerning them, theſe Governors hear, deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, and execute all in the Provinces by Deputies, unleſs there happen a hard caſe which they refer to the Emperor and his Councel; <hi>none governs where he is known, or where his Eſtate is.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe under Officers are permitted to rack the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, becauſe they muſt give their account at the end of their Office, when all that they have taken returus to the Emperors Coffers; few of them but come to the whip when they have done, under pretence of being puniſhed.</p>
               <p>There eight ſpecial perſons of worth and valour pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in the four bordering Towns, who have large Commiſſions, becauſe ſometimes their occaſions are ſuch by the ſudden Invaſion of an Enemie, that they have not time for direction: the City of <hi>Musko</hi> it ſelf is governed by the King and Councel, only for build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, impoſitions, keeping the ſtreets clean, there are ſome inferior Gentlemen appointed with the Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Conſtables; the Noble men are newly raiſed, and the people ſo cowed, that there is no likeliſhood of alteration; beſides the Emperor keeps the ſouldiery to himſelf by rendring them odious to the people, with whom therefore they never can Cloſe againſt him; to
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:106636:13"/>ſatisfie the humors of ſome Noble men, he maketh them Connſellors more for ſtate then any uſe he makes of them; having ſome privadoes whom he conſulteth day by day about the important affairs of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; others coming ſometimes who are of greater birth then wiſdom, taken in as may ſeem for that end, rather to furniſh the place with their honours and preſence then with their advice or Councel. Of the Councel are thirty one beſides two Lord Secretaries: the matters they debate are ſuch as are brought to them by the Lords of the Provinces from their ſeveral quarters, and the chief Officers of every Office of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, who may come into the Councel-Chamber, and inform them as occaſion incident to his Office doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire; beſides many private cauſes by way of ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation in great numbers are conſidered by them; they ſit about ſeven a clock in the morning, <hi>Mundays, Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſdaies</hi> and <hi>Fridaies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> 
                  <note place="margin">Revenue.</note> The rents are gathered by the Steward of thirty ſix Towns with the Crown lands and hundreds belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to them; theſe rents are paid partly in money, partly in grain, partly in proviſion of fleſh, Fiſh, and Foule, the ſurplus whereof is ſold by the Steward to the beſt hand, and runneth into the Emperors Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, which amounts to, 200000 <abbr>l.</abbr> a year, which pays wages and Salones, beſides this there are ſour Officers over the Taxes, gathering firſt <hi>Tagla</hi> or an impoſition on every meaſure of grain. 2. The <hi>Podal</hi> impoſed on every hundred in the Realme, both which amount to 400000 <abbr>l.</abbr> a year, beſides theſe are Officers for the Cuſtom which amounts to 340000 Rubbles, or makes a yea 160000 Rubbles, being gathered by the firſt Table of Cuſtomers 90000 to the ſecond, and 70000
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:106636:13"/>to the third, beſides this there is a Mullit ariſing from every Proceſſe in the Courts of Juſtice, which amounteth to 30000 Rubbels; the Remainder of Land Rents after the Army is paid amounts to 200000 <abbr>l.</abbr> yearly, ſo that there comes a million of mony clear, all charges paid to the Treaſury in the Caſtle of <hi>Musko,</hi> where the Emperors Mony, Plate, Jewels, Scepter, and bags ſealed with the Emperors ſeal; beſides forces and other commodities, with confiſcation, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounts to 500000 <abbr>l.</abbr> more, which are ſo great that a late Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror would ſay, <hi>That people were like his Beard, the oftner ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the thicker it grew, or like ſheep that muſt be ſhorn once a year at leaſt, to keep them from being overladen with their wool.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> 
                  <note place="margin">Policy to improve the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue.</note> 1. Theſe Emperors wink at the Officers exaction, until their time is expired that they may have it; they ſuck the people, and the Emperor ſucks them, and ſeems to make them a publick example (ſaying, <hi>Theſe good people are they that would eat you like bread</hi>) that they might confiſcate their goods, which a late Emperor did, calling an executioner, and bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding him kill a gooſe, and he cut off the mans legs firſt, then his arms, then his head, and there (ſaid the Emperor) is a gooſe ready dreſſed.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They make a ſhew of want, as this Emperors Father did, who being left very rich, coined his plate and ſold it, that he might ſeem to want mony, whereupon preſently out comes a Tax.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They encourage the ſubject to beſtow upon Monaſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ies all their wealth which they take upon occaſion without any noiſe: this I was told, that <hi>Juan Vaſilnwick,</hi> reſigned his Kingdom to one, whom he adviled to recal all Charters given to Monaſteries, which done he aſſumed the Government as if he diſliked this, and was content to renue their Charters, reſerving to himſelf as much of their Lands as himſelf thought good, whereby he got 30 millions of mony.</p>
               <p n="4">4. They ſend Meſſengers to engage the Commodities of the Provinces, buying them at ſmall Rates, and ſelling them at what they liſt. And ſo for forreign Commodities as I remember in the year 1645, when I traded in <hi>Baltick</hi> Sea: and they make a Monopoly of the Commodities he
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:106636:14"/>receives for Rent or Cuſtome, and to enhance the price o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them: And none muſt ſell their Commodities till the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors be all ſold.</p>
               <p n="5">5. He ſets up Drinking-hours, when men ſpend all their Eſtates, from which none may be called away, leſt they hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Emperours Revenue, where they lay up ſome twenty pound a man, and vow not to brave the Pot, until they have ſpent all, as they ſay, <hi>for the honour of the Emperour,</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. A Nobleman feigns himſelf robbed, and the City is fined 10000 Rubbles for its miſgovernment.</p>
               <p n="7">7. They ſend for what cannot be had, as for a peck of Flies to <hi>Muſco,</hi> and then fine the Inhabitants becauſe they do not what cannot be done.</p>
               <p n="8">8. One Emperor fined his Noblemen 30000 Rubbles be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he miſſed his hour one morning. Their exactions are ſo great, that I have ſeen ſo metimes when they have laid open their Commodities for a liking, to look ſtill behind and about them, whereof asking the cauſe, I found it to be this, That they doubted ſome of the Emperors Officers might be in company, and ſo a traine were laid upon them to prey up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their commodities: Therefore they drink and idle away the time (though able enough to endure labour) caring for no more then from hand to mouth. Yet there are ſome Merchants very rich there, dwelling far from Court, and worth 300000 Rubbles a piece, as I knew their brethren of late. The people are ignorant, that they may be more fit to be Slaves: Therefore in the year 1643 they removed all ſtrangers to the borders, leaſt they ſhould teach the people better Manners, Quallities, and more Wit. And none is to aſpire higher then his Fathers Trade.</p>
               <p n="9">9.
<note place="margin">Juſtice.</note> If any one is injured, he makes his ſupplication either to the Court of Aldermen, or the other two Courts, and thence hath a Writ for the other, who appears and pleads his own Cauſe, and if Evidence caſt him either by Witneſſes, or by the Plaintiffs kiſſing the Croſs upon the matter, he is ſent to the Serjeant, who irons him and cudgels him on the ſhins from Eight till Eleven every day, till he payes the money. Their Bills are theſe: <hi>I William White owe Juan Vaſilevel Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donor</hi>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:106636:14"/>100. <hi>Rubbels of going money of Musko without Intereſt, until the Councel Sunday: and if not paid then, I must pay five for ſix: upon this are witneſſes Gab. Jacovile ſin, An.</hi> 1662. This Bill have I written <hi>William White</hi> with my name to it. In criminal affairs they examine by tortures. and refer the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to King and Councel.</p>
               <p n="10">10. They riſe about four in the morning, and worſhip,
<note place="margin">Their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour.</note> and then to buſineſs, and then to their wives, and then to Dinner, where their food is rather plentiful then curious, with which they drink plentifully, after which they ſleep two hours daily, which would kill them, but that they ſweat it out in hot Baths: out of which they can go to the cold air, yea and water too in the winter time. They allow their women money for paint: They wear Caps cloſe to <hi>their heads, and are ſhaven,</hi> unleſs they be in diſpleaſure with the Emperour when they let their hair grow: Over the Cap he weareth a wide Cap of black Furre, with a long Bonnet within it. About their necks, Collours beſet with Pearls and precious ſtones. Next over his ſhirt, (which is curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly wrought, becauſe he ſtripeth himſelf in the Summer time) is a light garment of Silk made down to the knees, buttoned before, and then a cloſe Coat buttoned, and girt with a <hi>Perſian</hi> Girdle, whereat he hangs his knives and ſpoons: over which he weareth a looſe Garment of rich ſilk, furred and faced about with gold lace: Their noice is infinite, who cry, <hi>Give me and kill me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ruſſian Embaſſy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent. in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Eliz: ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> The <hi>Ruſſe</hi> maketh ſmall regard of his word, neither be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth what another ſpeaks, nor ſpeaketh any thing worthy to be believed: however the Engliſh have upon the account of Trade in the <hi>Baltick Sea,</hi> and intereſt in the Northren parts, made very much of their Embaſſadours here three times.</p>
               <p n="11">11. I. In Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time, <hi>Anno</hi> 1589.
<note place="margin">By K. James</note> who ſent the Maſter of the Ceremoney with the Lord Treaſurer, the Lord Chamberlain with a great Court-train to meet him at the Tower, from whence he was conducted by the Aldermen in Scarlet, with the ſeveral Companies in <hi>chains</hi> through the City to <hi>Durham</hi>-houſe, where they were entertained at the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:106636:15"/>
                  <hi>Queens charge,</hi> until they were conducted by the Earl of <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſexes</hi> andience, which they did in all humble manner, as they ſaid to the <hi>ſecond maid in the world,</hi> —</p>
               <p n="2">II. In King <hi>James</hi> time, <hi>Novemb.</hi> 5. 1617. a <hi>Ruſsian</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour with his Aſſiſtant the Councellour of <hi>Muſcovy,</hi> was received at Tower-Wharf by the Lord <hi>Cempton,</hi> having been firſt received at <hi>Graveſ end</hi> by Mr. <hi>Richard Smith</hi> chief of the <hi>Muſcovy</hi> Campany: They were welcomed at Landing with the Ordnances of the Tower and Ships, and were met on Tower-hill by the Aldermen in Scarlet, and other <hi>Citizens</hi> in velvet <hi>Coats</hi> and <hi>Chains</hi> of gold, and thence conducted to his houſe in <hi>Biſhopgate</hi>-ſtreet, whence they preſented the King and Queen with 4000 <abbr>l.</abbr> ſterling in gifts.</p>
               <p>Now he hath been entertained in like manner attended by 12000 men in arms,
<note place="margin">K. <hi>C.</hi> 2d.</note> and hath had audience, and preſented the King with Cordage, Furs, Beaſts and Birds, worth 1500 <abbr>l.</abbr> intending to treat with his Majeſty about the Northren Affairs of Trade, Peace and War.</p>
               <p>His Majeſty ſent the Maſter of the Ceremonies, with many Coaches more of the Nobility to conduct him to the City, whence he was met by the Aldermen and Citizens on horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>back with Trumpets: the City all along being lined with 25000 Trained-band and Auxilliaries: and he was conduct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>York</hi>-houſe, whence he was conducted to Audience, <hi>Decem.</hi> 1. 1662. which he made in very humble manner, ſtooping and knocking his forehead againſt the ground be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the King, who ſat in great State, environed with the Nobility, as the Sun with ſtars: the Glory of his friends, the envy of his foes, and the wonder of the world.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
